<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Marca1><texto_geral><titulo_cap_texto>Facts and figures</titulo_cap_texto> <imagem><imagem>&lt;ID005-G001-2020-EM-ING-1-L1-FU-U7-C19.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><legenda>The Internet is today the most important communication platform in the world. And when it comes to the Internet, it means e-mail, messaging, websites, among many other forms of interaction between people. </legenda><fonte>Source: W3 Techs Web Technology Surveys.<caracter_italico> Historical trends in the usage of content languages for websites</caracter_italico>. Available at: &lt;https://w3techs.com/technologies/history_overview/content_language&gt;. Accessed on: July, 13rd, 2021. </fonte><legenda> </legenda><texto_geral>What were you doing when you heard an English word for the first time? When and where did you speak your first sentence in this language? There is a slight chance you will remember such specific information, but you may remember your first English teacher, a nursery rhyme you learned as a kid, or even the lines of your most beloved movie or song in English. And so could possibly do the 378 million native speakers and the 743 million people around the globe who speak English as a second language. Considering there are approximately 7 billion people in the world, this is relevant data. </texto_geral><texto_geral>Currently, people who use English as their mother tongue make up less than 10% of the world’s population; nevertheless, in terms of the quantity of transmitted information, English is the leader by far. Throughout the world, it is studied as a foreign language and employed by a majority of Internet users, used in most movies both in original recording or subtitles, and found in music, broadcasting, technical and scientific periodicals.  </texto_geral><texto_geral>It is known that a working knowledge of English is required in many fields and occupations, and that’s why teaching English at least at a basic level is mandatory in a variety of countries. Due to globalization, e-mail exchanges, meetings and negotiations are mostly performed in English. Therefore, speaking the language can be a breakthrough for career growth, or even for getting a job, either in national or international companies. If you were thinking about improving your skills but weren’t feeling inspired, we hope you change your mind and find a connection with this powerful international language. •	</texto_geral><texto_bullets>How much time do you invest in learning English? Do you think it is enough?  •	</texto_bullets><texto_bullets>In addition to studying at the regular school, paying attention to classes and doing the exercises, what else do you do to improve your English skills? •	</texto_bullets><texto_bullets>What careers can you choose if you speak English? </texto_bullets><boxe_02_texto>Neste capítulo, serão abordadas as habilidades <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG301</boxe_06_texto>, <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG402</boxe_06_texto>, <boxe_06_texto>EM13LGG403</boxe_06_texto>. </boxe_02_texto><boxe_31>Dive in <boxe_31_titulo1>Past Continuous tense </boxe_31_titulo1><boxe_31_texto><secao_01_titulo1></secao_01_titulo1>On many suspense movies, when a crime has been committed and the detectives or officers need to investigate suspects in order to find out if they have alibis, they ask questions such as the following: </boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><imagem><imagem>&lt;what_wer.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_texto>We use the Past Continuous tense (also called Past Progressive tense) to describe an action that was in progress in the past. When we use the Past Continuous tense, our listener usually knows or understands what time we are talking about. The answer for the previous question, for example, could be: </boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><imagem><imagem>&lt;i_wad.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_texto><credito></credito>We often use the Past Continuous tense to “set the scene” in stories. We use it to describe the background situation that was happening when the action began. Often, the story starts with the Past Continuous tense and then moves into the Past Simple tense. Here is an example: </boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><imagem><imagem>&lt;It_was_night.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_titulo1><credito></credito>Verb “be” for the Past Continuous </boxe_31_titulo1><boxe_31_texto><secao_02_titulo1></secao_02_titulo1><secao_texto>The structure of the Past Continuous is always: was/were + verb + -ing. </secao_texto><secao_texto>It is always good to remind you that we use was with the pronouns I / he / she / it and were with the pronouns we / you / they. </secao_texto>We always use a singular verb after the indefinite pronouns: </boxe_31_texto><boxe_31_texto></boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><imagem><imagem>&lt;everyone_was.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_titulo1><credito></credito>Repetition and irritation with “always” </boxe_31_titulo1><boxe_31_texto><secao_02_titulo1></secao_02_titulo1>The Past Continuous with words such as “always” or “constantly” expresses the idea of something irritating or shocking that was happening in the past, and it shows a negative emotion. Remember: the words “always” or “constantly” go between “be” and “verb + -ing.” </boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><imagem><imagem>&lt;Billy_Elliot.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_titulo1><credito></credito>Forms </boxe_31_titulo1><secao_01_titulo1></secao_01_titulo1><imagem><imagem>&lt;Affirmative.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><credito></credito><imagem><imagem>&lt;negative.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><credito></credito><imagem><imagem>&lt;interrogative.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_31_titulo1><credito></credito>Grammaring </boxe_31_titulo1><boxe_31_texto><secao_02_titulo1></secao_02_titulo1>Read the text to answers the questions that follow. </boxe_31_texto><secao_texto></secao_texto><secao_titulo_citado>‘Globish’: why France has a love-hate relationship with global English </secao_titulo_citado><secao_texto_citado>A Parisian book fair’s promotion of Globish may have sparked outrage among critics, but it’s not the first time the French have promoted simplified English. </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>French writers were up in arms this week after the Salon du Livre book fair in Paris announced a celebration of young adult books that would feature a “Bookroom”, a “Photobooth”, and even a “Bookquizz”, a prospect so exciting it needs two zs. Such anglicisms, critics wrote, were an “unconscionable act of cultural vandalism”, employing the “sub-English known as Globish”. </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>It is a lamentable irony, then, that Globish has been so energetically popularised by a Frenchman. In 2004, the former IBM executive Jean-Paul Nerrière began selling his system of simplified English (only 1,500 words) to students around the world. (Globish is a portmanteau of “globe” and “English”.) The earliest attested use of the term, however, described in 1997 a more natural linguistic hybridisation of various “non-western forms of English” that had become just as “creative and lively” as the standard tongue. </secao_texto_citado><fonte>“‘Globish’: why France has a love-hate relationship with global English”. The Guardian, February 8th, 2019. Available at: &lt;www.theguardian.com/books/2019/feb/08/word-of-the-week-globish&gt;. Accessed on: July 13rd, 2021. © Copyright Guardian News &amp; Media Ltd 2019. </fonte><boxe_31_texto>“Globish” is therefore both a trademark for one man’s singular vision of international communication, and a way of describing the branching of English into multiple exotic planetary species. But the literary Parisians see it simply as yet more Anglo-Saxon cultural imperialism. Well, as the French do sometimes say, c’est la life. </boxe_31_texto><exercicio_enunciado><secao_texto></secao_texto><secao_exercicio_numerador>1	</secao_exercicio_numerador>Answer the questions about the text. </exercicio_enunciado><item_lista><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>Take a quick look at the headline and answer: Are the French always happy about Globish? Explain with an excerpt from the text. </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito>According to the author, how was the use of the term “Globish” described in 1997? </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>Who popularized the term “Globish” in the early 2000’s? </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>How do Parisians see Globish? </item_lista><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>2	</secao_exercicio_numerador>Choose the correct alternative for the sentences. </exercicio_enunciado><item_lista><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>My brother and sister  playing tennis at 11 a.m. yesterday. </item_lista><boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio_item></secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito>	 are	   <caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> was  	<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> were </boxe_31_texto><item_lista><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito> you still working at 7 p.m. last night? </item_lista><boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio_item></secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> Were		<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> Are	<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> Was </boxe_31_texto><item_lista><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>Why  he having lunch at 4 p.m.? </item_lista><boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio_item></secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> was		<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> does	<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> were </boxe_31_texto><item_lista><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>Was he not  his homework? </item_lista><boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio_item></secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> doing		<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> do	<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> done </boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>e)	</caracter_negrito>Snow  lightly. Suddenly a reindeer appeared. </secao_exercicio_item><boxe_31_texto><caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> fell	<caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> was falling   <caracter_negrito>(   )</caracter_negrito> is falling </boxe_31_texto><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>3	</secao_exercicio_numerador>Fill in the spaces with the proper verbs in the correct tenses. </exercicio_enunciado><boxe_31_texto><secao_exercicio>Yesterday, it  (rain) all day, that’s why Lucy  (stay) inside the house, she couldn’t go outside. She  (want) to call her friends, but the rain interrupted the telephone service.  </secao_exercicio><secao_exercicio>She  (try) to keep busy in the house, and  (pick up) a book to read. When she  (read) the book, the electricity  (go) out. Then, she  (start) to meditate, because lights  (be) necessary to do so. After she  (finish) her meditation, she  (have) no more ideas. So, she  (sit) near the window and  (look) at the rain. </secao_exercicio><secao_exercicio>While she  (look) at the rain, the phone  (ring). It  (be) Mary, her best friend. Lucy and Mary  (talk) on the phone,  (look) at the rain and  (talk) about the film they both  (see) the night before. They  (have) fun! </secao_exercicio><secao_exercicio>After some time, they  (hang) up the phone. It  (be) still  (rain). But she  (do/not) mind, because it  (be) lunchtime, and her mom always  (come) home for lunch. Lucy  (set) the table when Mrs. Jones  (arrive) with food from the restaurant where she  (works). How delicious! They  (eat) when the rain finally  (stop). After lunch, she could leave the house and walk in</secao_exercicio></boxe_31_texto></boxe_31> <boxe_33>practice it! <exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>1	</secao_exercicio_numerador><caracter_negrito>UEL-PR 2019</caracter_negrito> Texto para a questão 1. </exercicio_enunciado><secao_titulo_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_titulo_citado><secao_texto_citado>By Quique Avilés </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>by virtue, coincidence or heaven </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>words jumping out of my mouth </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>stepping on each other </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>enjoying being a voice for the message </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>expecting conclusions </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>into heavy accent bits of confusion </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>into miracles and accidents </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>saying things that hurt the heart </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>drowning in a language that lives, jumps, </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>translates </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided by nature </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>by our crazy desire to triumph and conquer </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>This tongue is cut up into equal pieces </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>one wants to curse and sing out loud </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>the other one simply wants to ask for water </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>one side likes to party </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>the other one takes refuge in praying </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>english of the funny sounds </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>funny sounds in english </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>sounds funny in english </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>in funny english sounds </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue sometimes acts like two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>and it goes crazy </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>not knowing which side should be speaking </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>which side translating </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>a border patrol runs through the middle </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>frisking words </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>asking for proper identification </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>checking for pronunciation </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>My tongue is divided into two </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>I like my tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>it says what feels right </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>I like my tongue </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>it says what feels right </secao_texto_citado><fonte>Quique Avilés, “My tongue is divided into two” from The Immigrant Museum. Copyright © 2004 by Quique Avilés. Reprinted by permission of Raices de Papel. Source: The Immigrant Museum (Rain Coast Books, 2004). </fonte><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio>“My tongue is divided into two” foi escrito por Quique Avilés, nascido em El Salvador e radicado nos Estados Unidos desde 1980, quando tinha 15 anos de idade. </secao_exercicio>Como essa identidade do autor é retratada no poema? Justifique sua resposta com trechos do texto.</exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio> </secao_exercicio><secao_exercicio> </secao_exercicio><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>2	</secao_exercicio_numerador><caracter_negrito>Uece 2014</caracter_negrito> The students  studying now, but two hours ago they  playing football.  </exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio></secao_exercicio><item_lista><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>were, are </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito>were, will be </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>are, were </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>are, have been </item_lista><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>3	</secao_exercicio_numerador><caracter_negrito>Enem 2014 </caracter_negrito>Texto para a questão 3. </exercicio_enunciado><secao_titulo_citado>If You Can’t Master English, Try Globish </secao_titulo_citado><secao_texto_citado>PARIS – It happens all the time: during an airport delay the man to the left, a Korean perhaps, starts talking to the man opposite, who might be Colombian, and soon they are chatting away in what seems to be English. But the native English speaker sitting between them cannot understand a word. </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>They don’t know it, but the Korean and the Colombian are speaking Globish, the latest addition to the 6,800 languages that are said to be spoken across the world. Not that its inventor, Jean-Paul Nerrière, considers it a proper language.  </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>“It is not a language, it is a tool,” he says. “A language is the vehicle of a culture. Globish doesn’t want to be that at all. It is a means of communication.”  </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>Nerrière doesn’t see Globish in the same light as utopian efforts such as Kosmos, Volapuk, Novial or staunch Esperanto. Nor should it be confused with barbaric Algol (for Algorithmic language). It is a sort of English lite: a means of simplifying the language and giving it rules so it can be understood by all.  </secao_texto_citado><fonte>BLUME, M. Disponível em: www.nytimes.com. Acesso em: 28 out. 2013 (fragmento). </fonte><exercicio_enunciado>Considerando as ideias apresentadas no texto, o <caracter_italico>Globish</caracter_italico> (<caracter_italico>Global English</caracter_italico>) é uma variedade da língua inglesa que  </exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio></secao_exercicio><item_lista><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>tem status de língua por refletir uma cultura global.  </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito>facilita o entendimento entre o falante nativo e o não nativo.  </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>tem as mesmas características de projetos utópicos como o esperanto.  </item_lista><item_lista><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>altera a estrutura do idioma para possibilitar a comunicação internacional. </item_lista></boxe_33> </texto_geral><boxe_33>practice it! <exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>1	</secao_exercicio_numerador><caracter_negrito>UFES 2016</caracter_negrito> In the short texts, people describe situations involving cultural misunderstandings in foreign countries. Fill in the gaps using the cues in parentheses.  </exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio></secao_exercicio><secao_exercicio_item><secao_texto_citado>A British colleague invited me to join his friends after work. We  (GO) to a pub where he bought me a drink and he suggested a meal in a restaurant. At the end of the meal, I was very surprised to see everyone  (TAKE OUT) their wallets to pay the waiter. My friend expected me to pay as well, but I feel it was very mean of him not to pay for me as he invited me. (Kenji, Japan) </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>I  (VISIT) Germany for the first time and I decided to pay my most important customer a visit. She  (INVITE) me for quite some time. I decided to take her a beautiful bunch of twelve red roses and her husband a bottle of wine. I gave her the flowers, but she just looked embarrassed. (Douglas, Scotland) </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>When I was at university in England, my English tutor invited a group of us to her home. I didn’t want to make any mistakes, such as  (STAY) too late. So when she brought us a drink before we began the meal, I said, ‘Thank you for inviting us to your home and for inviting us to dinner. Could you tell me when we can leave?’ She laughed and said, ‘So, you can’t wait  (LEAVE)?’. (Lu, China) </secao_texto_citado><secao_texto_citado>I have recently arrived in the USA and don’t have many friends yet, so, I was pleased to meet a really nice American in the college cafeteria the other week. We had a long conversation, she told me the story of her life, she showed me photos of her family, and left me her address. The following week I saw her, but although she smiled and said ‘Hi!’ in a friendly way, she went and sat with other friends. I feel very hurt.  (SHE/EXPECT) me to call on her? I feel I need an invitation. (Hana, Lebanon) </secao_texto_citado>I was sitting in a bus in Bristol when an elderly lady got on the bus. It  (BE) crowded and there weren’t any seats. A middle-aged man said very loudly, ‘Would you offer the lady your seat, please?’ Why didn’t he give her his seat? (Carlos, Spain) </secao_exercicio_item><exercicio_enunciado><secao_texto_citado></secao_texto_citado><caracter_negrito>Unicamp 2020 </caracter_negrito>Texto para a questão 2. </exercicio_enunciado><legenda><secao_exercicio></secao_exercicio>O <caracter_italico>site</caracter_italico> “Urban Dictionary” apresenta definições de palavras e expressões que, apesar de serem usadas popularmente, ainda não foram oficialmente dicionarizadas. O exemplo abaixo faz alusão ao Brexit, isto é, à saída do Reino Unido da União Europeia.</legenda><secao_exercicio> </secao_exercicio><imagem><imagem>&lt;LUMEN_Q005-2020-EM-ING-2S-V3-U2-C6.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><fonte>(Disponível em https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Doing%20the%20Brexit. Acessado em 11/05/2019.) </fonte><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>2	</secao_exercicio_numerador>Com relação ao exemplo apresentado, entende-se que Taylor estava “fazendo o Brexit” porque  </exercicio_enunciado><item_lista><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>se despediu, mas demorou a ir embora da festa.  </secao_exercicio_item><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito>saiu “à francesa” da festa, isto é, saiu discretamente.  </secao_exercicio_item><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>se despediu, mas anunciou que demoraria a sair da festa. </secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>saiu “à francesa” da festa, isto é, saiu depois de muito tempo. </item_lista><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_item></secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>Unicamp 2020</caracter_negrito> Texto para a questão 3.  </exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio></secao_exercicio><imagem><imagem>&lt;LUMEN_Q004-2020-EM-ING-2S-V3-U2-C6.png&gt;</imagem> </imagem><boxe_texto_citado>There are approximately 70 million pet dogs and 74 million pet cats in the U.S., a country where 20 men and women are assaulted per minute. In one survey, 71 percent of domestic violence victims reported that their abuser also targeted pets. In one study of families under investigation for suspected child abuse, researchers found that pet abuse had occurred in 88 percent of these families.  </boxe_texto_citado><legenda></legenda><fonte>(Adaptado de https://www.humanesociety.org/resources/animal- cruelty-facts-and-stats. Acessado em 11/05/2019.)  </fonte><exercicio_enunciado><secao_exercicio_numerador>3	</secao_exercicio_numerador>O objetivo do texto é destacar a relação entre </exercicio_enunciado><item_lista><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>a)	</caracter_negrito>aumento do número de animais domésticos e de casos de crueldade contra os animais.  </secao_exercicio_item><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>b)	</caracter_negrito>violência doméstica e famílias investigadas por crueldade contra os animais.  </secao_exercicio_item><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>c)	</caracter_negrito>condenações por abuso infantil e crueldade contra os animais. </secao_exercicio_item><secao_exercicio_item><caracter_negrito>d)	</caracter_negrito>casos de violência doméstica e crueldade contra os animais.</secao_exercicio_item></item_lista></boxe_33></Marca1>
